Hal H. Empie Papers
Hal H. Empie Papers
1937-1986
Empie, Hal H., 1909-
2.7 linear ft.
Papers of the American cartoonist, illustrator and painter including drawings, cartoons, photographs and printed material
148965
Biographical History
Hart Haller "Hal" Empie (1909-2002) was an American cartoonist, illustrator, painter, and pharmacist.
Hal Empie was born outside of Safford, Arizona Territory on March 26, 1909. In 1920, Empie and his family moved to Safford proper where his parents opened a hotel. As a teenager, Empie went to work as an assistant in a drug store. He held this job until he went to study medicine at the University of Arizona in 1927. Empie left the university to get married but became a licensed pharmacist at age 20 after attending the Capitol College of Pharmacy in Denver. Empie is said to have been the youngest licensed pharmacist in Arizona history.
After working for a few years in Solomonville, Arizona and suffering financial setbacks, Empie began to pursue art for extra income and in 1934 Empie moved to Duncan, Arizona to become a drugstore manager. Several years later Empie took over ownership of the store and renamed it the Art Gallery Drug which he would run for the next 50 years while he continued to work as an artist on the side.
Empie depicted life in Arizona in its earliest decades of statehood both in caricature and in landscape paintings. In the 1930s, Empie began producing Western-themed cartoon postcards through Empie Kartoon Kards. But Empie turned his focus to his love of oil painting and Empie worked to promote the creation of Arizona related art by Arizona artists.
Empie left Duncan and closed the Art Gallery Drug and moved to Tubac, Arizona in the 1980s where he opened the Hal Empie Studio & Gallery. In the late 1990s, Empie’s eyesight began to deteriorate but he adapted his tools and techniques so he could continue to paint. Empie, a prolific painter, began selling his paintings as a teenager and was primarily a self-taught artist aside from a few weeks of art courses in the early 1950s.
Empie’s life and work has been profiled in numerous publications and exhibited at regional galleries as well at the Tucson Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art in New York City. A biography of Empie, Arizona's Hal Empie, His Life, His Times and His Art was published by the Arizona Historical Foundation in 2001 with a foreword by Supreme Court Justice Sandra Day O'Connor.
Hal Empie died on March 26, 2002.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hal H. Empie Papers are organized into 3 series. The first series, Artwork consists of 2 original drawings and 11 original cartoons. Empie used marker for the drawings and ink for the cartoons. The second series, Photographs contains 8 photographs and 2 sheets of negatives. The final series, Printed Material contains material related to Empie's career as a cartoonist and painter as well as biographical material.
Arrangement of the Collection
The artwork is arranged by medium. The photographs are arranged by subject and the printed material is arranged as it was received.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
One published book, Way Out West (date unknown) and one exhibition catalog, Echoes of Arizona: Hal Empie One Man Show (Presido Gallery: 1986) have been removed from this collection and sent to Rare Books.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Cartoonists; Empie, Hal H., 1909-; Art Gallery Drug Store (Duncan, Ariz.); Empie Kartoon Kards.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Arizona.; Illustrators -- Arizona.; Illustrators -- United States.; Painters -- Arizona.; Painters -- United States.; Postcards.; West (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Biography files.; Cartoons (humorous images); Catalogs (documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Drawings (visual works); Photographs.; Prints (visual works); Artists.; Cartoonists.; Illustrators.; Painters.; Pharmacists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Hal Empie, 1968, 1986.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Drawings
    - "Juan's Home", 1950 (Oversize 1)
    - "Oscar", 1955 (Oversize 1)
  - Cartoons
    - Life's About Ore, 1937 (Oversize 1)
    - Greetings from Our Back Yard- Home on the Range, 1939 (Oversize 1)
    - A La Carte, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Land of the Brave, undated (Oversize 1)
    - The Local Sunbeam, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Man of Distinkshun, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Way Out West- With Th' Apache Injuns, undated (Oversize 1)
    - untitled (woman with baby), undated (Oversize 1)
    - Am On Maneuvers Will Report Later, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Feelin' Our Oats, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Strange Country Out Here 'Tain't Bubble Gum It's Soap Weed, undated (Map-case 1, Drawer 100)
- Photographs
  - Self, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Art Gallery Drug, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Paintings, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Negatives of cartoons, undated (Box 1)
- Printed Material
  - Empie Kartoon-Kards catalog, undated (Box 1)
  - "Gettin' a Mite Chilly" card from Hal Empie Studio with biographical information on inside, undated (Box 1)
  - El Presido Gallery announcement of limited edition Empie print, undated (Box 1)
  - "'The Robe' part of exhibition by Duncan artist Empie", 1984 Mar; Arizona Daily Star article (Box 1)
  - "Born to Create: Pharmacist Pursues Artistic Yearnings", 5 Dec 1985; The State of Art article (Box 1)
  - El Presido Gallery catalog, Echoes of Arizona- Hal Empie One Man Show, 1986; photocopy of cover and title page. Original located in Rare Books. (Box 1)
  - Way Out West book, undated; photocopy of cover and title page. Original located in Rare Books. (Box 1)
  - The Grand Canyon in July - South Rim, undated; print of Empie's painting (Oversize 2)
  - On Blue River, undated; print of Empie's painting (Oversize 2)